I am British.
أنا بريطاني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Never before has the phrase "I am British" elicited so much pity.
لم يحدث من قبل أن أثارت عبارة "أنا بريطاني" كل هذا القدر من الشفقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I come from an island where many of us like to believe
أتيت من جزيرة حيث يميل أغلبنا إلى التصديق
there's been a lot of continuity over the last thousand years.
بوجود قدر كبير من الاستمرارية خلال الألف سنة الماضية.
We tend to have historically imposed change on others
تاريخياً، كنا نميل إلى فرض التغيير على الآخرين
but done much less of it ourselves.
مقابل القليل جداً لأنفسنا.
So it came as an immense shock to me
لذلك كان الأمر بمثابة صدمة هائلة بالنسبة لي
when I woke up on the morning of June 24
عندما استقيظت في صبيحة الرابع والعشرين من شهر يونيو
to discover that my country had voted to leave the European Union,
لأكتشف أن بلادي صوتت لصالح مغادرة الإتحاد الأوروبي،
my Prime Minister had resigned,
وأن رئيس وزرائي استقال،
and Scotland was considering a referendum
وأن سكتلندا تنظر في أمر الإستفتاء مجدداً،
that could bring to an end the very existence of the United Kingdom.
الشيء الذي قد يعني نهاية المملكة المتحدة تماماً.
So that was an immense shock for me,
لذلك كانت تلك صدمة هائلة بالنسبة لي،
and it was an immense shock for many people,
وكانت كذلك بالنسبة لعدد كبير من الناس،
but it was also something that, over the following several days,
ولكن الأمر وخلال الأيام التالية له
created a complete political meltdown
خلق انهيارا سياسيا تاما
in my country.
في بلادي.
There were calls for a second referendum,
كانت هناك دعوات لإجراء استفتاء ثاني،
almost as if, following a sports match,
وكأننا نتابع مباراة رياضية،
we could ask the opposition for a replay.
حين نطلب من المعارضة إعادة اللعبة.
Everybody was blaming everybody else.
كان كل واحد يلوم الآخر.
People blamed the Prime Minister
كان الناس يلومون رئيس الوزراء
for calling the referendum in the first place.
على طرح أمرالإستفتاء من الأساس.
They blamed the leader of the opposition for not fighting it hard enough.
تعرض رئيس المعارضة للوم لعدم بذله الجهد الكافي لوقف الأمر.
The young accused the old.
اتهم الشباب الكبار.
The educated blamed the less well-educated.
لام المتعلمون من هم أقل تعليماً.
That complete meltdown was made even worse
أصبح أمر ذلك الإنهيار السياسي أسوء
by the most tragic element of it:
نتيجةً للعنصر الأكثر مأساوية فيه:
levels of xenophobia and racist abuse in the streets of Britain
ظهر رهاب الأجانب والاعتداءات العنصرية في شوارع بريطانيا
at a level that I have never seen before
بمستويات لم أعهدها من قبل
in my lifetime.
في حياتي.
People are now talking about whether my country is becoming a Little England,
يتحدث الناس حالياً ما إذا كانت بلادي في طريقها أن تصبح إنجلترا الصغرى فقط،
or, as one of my colleagues put it,
أو كما قال أحد زملائي،
whether we're about to become a 1950s nostalgia theme park
ما إذا كنا في طريقنا أن نصبح كما في العام 1915
floating in the Atlantic Ocean.
عائمين على المحيط الأطلسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But my question is really,
ولكن سؤالي حقاً،
should we have the degree of shock that we've experienced since?
هل كان من الطبيعي أن نشعر بمقدار الصدمة الذي شعرنا به حينها؟
Was it something that took place overnight?
هل حدث ذلك بين ليلة وضحاها؟
Or are there deeper structural factors that have led us to where we are today?
أم أن للأمر عوامل هيكلية عميقة تسببت في ما نحن فيه اليوم؟
So I want to take a step back and ask two very basic questions.
لذلك، أود أخذ خطوة للخلف وطرح سؤالين أساسيين للغاية.
First, what does Brexit represent,
أولاً، ما الذي يمثله خروج بريطانيا
not just for my country,
ليس فقط لبلدي،
but for all of us around the world?
بل لنا جميعاً حول العالم؟
And second, what can we do about it?
ثانياً، ماذا عسانا أن نفعل حيال الأمر؟
How should we all respond?
كيف يجب أن نتصرف؟
So first, what does Brexit represent?
لذا كبداية، ما الذي يعنيه خروج بريطانيا؟
Hindsight is a wonderful thing.
الإدراك المتأخر شيء رائع.
Brexit teaches us many things about our society
يعلمنا خروج بريطانيا العديد من الأشياء عن مجتمعنا
and about societies around the world.
وكذلك عن المجتمعات الأخرى حول العالم.
It highlights in ways that we seem embarrassingly unaware of
حيث يسلط الضوء بشكل يوضح جهلنا إلى حد محير
how divided our societies are.
بعمق الإنقسام الحاصل في مجتماعتنا.
The vote split along lines of age, education, class and geography.
انقسم التصويت على أسس كالعمر والتعليم والطبقة والجغرافيا.
Young people didn't turn out to vote in great numbers,
حيث تبين أن الشباب لم يصوتوا بكثافة،
but those that did wanted to remain.
ما عدا أولئك الذين أرادوا البقاء.
Older people really wanted to leave the European Union.
أما كبار السن فقد أرادوا فعلياً مغادرة الإتحاد الأوروبي.
Geographically, it was London and Scotland that most strongly committed
جغرافياً، كانت لندن وسكتلاند الأكثر التزاماً
to being part of the European Union,
بالبقاء ضمن الاتحاد الأوروبي،
while in other parts of the country there was very strong ambivalence.
بينما في باقي أجزاء البلاد كانت هناك درجة عالية من الإزدواجية.
Those divisions are things we really need to recognize and take seriously.
نحتاج بشدة إلى التعرف على هذه الانقسامات وكذلك أخذها على محمل الجد.
But more profoundly, the vote teaches us something
ولكن بشكل أعمق، يعلمنا التصويت شيئاً
about the nature of politics today.
حول طبيعة السياسة اليوم.
Contemporary politics is no longer just about right and left.
السياسة المعاصرة اليوم تتعدى فكرة اليمين واليسار.
It's no longer just about tax and spend.
كما أنها لم تعد مجرد ضرائب ونفقات.
It's about globalization.
بل تعنى بالعولمة.
The fault line of contemporary politics is between those that embrace globalization
خط الصدع في السياسة المعاصرة يتمثل بين أولئك الذين يحتضنون العولمة
and those that fear globalization.
وأولئك الذين يخشونها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If we look at why those who wanted to leave --
إذا ما نظرنا في أمر أولئك الذين أرادوا المغادرة
we call them "Leavers," as opposed to "Remainers" --
ونسميهم "المغادرون" مقابل "الباقون"--
we see two factors in the opinion polls
نجد عاملين في استطلاعات الرأي
that really mattered.
يمثلان أهمية كبيرة.
The first was immigration, and the second sovereignty,
أولهما الهجرة وثانيهما السيادة،
and these represent a desire for people to take back control of their own lives
وهما يمثلان رغبة الناس في استعادة السيطرة على حياتهم
and the feeling that they are unrepresented by politicians.
والإحساس بأنهم مهمشون من قبل السياسيين.
But those ideas are ones that signify fear and alienation.
ولكن هذه الأفكار هي نفسها التي تدل على الخوف والعزلة.
They represent a retreat back towards nationalism and borders
فهي تمثل تراجعاُ نحو القومية والحدود
in ways that many of us would reject.
بطرق سيرفضها الكثيرون منا.
What I want to suggest is the picture is more complicated than that,
ما أود الإشارة له هو أن الصورة أكثر تعقيداً مما تبدو عليه،
that liberal internationalists,
حيث أن الأمميين الليبراليين
like myself, and I firmly include myself in that picture,
مثلي، وأشمل نفسي بشكل قاطع في الصورة،
need to write ourselves back into the picture
بحاجة إلى العودة إلى الصورة
in order to understand how we've got to where we are today.
من أجل أن نفهم كيف وصلنا إلى ما نحن فيه اليوم.
When we look at the voting patterns across the United Kingdom,
فإذا ما نظرنا إلى عينات التصويت عبر المملكة المتحدة،
we can visibly see the divisions.
نستطيع بكل وضوح رؤية الانقسامات.
The blue areas show Remain
توضح المناطق الزرقاء "الباقين"
and the red areas Leave.
والمناطق الحمراء "المغادرين".
When I looked at this,
عندما ألقيت نظرة على هذه،
what personally struck me was the very little time in my life
الشيء الذي صدمني حقاً هو الفترة الزمنية البسيطة جداً من حياتي
I've actually spent in many of the red areas.
التي قضيتها في كثير من المناطق الحمراء.
I suddenly realized that, looking at the top 50 areas in the UK
أدركت فجأة، بالنظر إلى المناطق الخمسين الأولى في بريطانيا
that have the strongest Leave vote,
التي حازت على أكبر نسبة تصويت لصالح المغادرة،
I've spent a combined total of four days of my life in those areas.
أني قضيت ما مجموعه أربعة أيام فقط من حياتي في تلك المناطق.
In some of those places,
في بعض هذه المناطق،
I didn't even know the names of the voting districts.
لم أكن أعرف حتى أسماء الدوائر الإنتخابية.
It was a real shock to me,
لقد كانت تلك صدمة بالنسبة لي،
and it suggested that people like me
فقد دل ذلك على أن الأشخاص مثلي
who think of ourselves as inclusive, open and tolerant,
الذين يرون أنهم شاملون ومنفتحون ومتسامحون،
perhaps don't know our own countries and societies
ربما لا ندري بالشكل الكافي عن بلداننا ومجتماعتنا
nearly as well as we like to believe.
بنفس القدر الذي نحب تصديقه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And the challenge that comes from that is we need to find a new way
التحدي الناتج من ذلك هو أننا بحاجة إلى إيجاد طريقة جديدة
to narrate globalization to those people,
لإيصال فكرة العولمة لهؤلاء الأشخاص،
to recognize that for those people who have not necessarily been to university,
ولكي نعترف أنه بالنسبة لهؤلاء الأِشخاص الذين ليسوا بالضرورة خريجي جامعات،
who haven't necessarily grown up with the Internet,
ولم ينشأوا بالضرورة في وجود الإنترنت،
that don't get opportunities to travel,
ولم تتح لهم فرص السفر،
they may be unpersuaded by the narrative that we find persuasive
ربما هم غير مقتنعون بالقصة التي نجدها مقنعة بالنسبة لنا
in our often liberal bubbles.
في فقاعاتنا الليبرالية المعتادة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It means that we need to reach out more broadly and understand.
ذلك يعني أننا بحاجة إلى الوصول على نطاق أوسع والفهم كذلك.
In the Leave vote, a minority have peddled the politics of fear and hatred,
بالنسبة لمن غادروا، فإن أقلية روجت لسياسة الخوف والكراهية،
creating lies and mistrust
خالقين جواً من الأكاذيب وعدم الثقة
around, for instance, the idea that the vote on Europe
في الجوار، على سبيل المثال، فكرة أن البقاء ضمن أوروبا
could reduce the number of refugees and asylum-seekers coming to Europe,
قد يقلل من عدد اللاجئين وطالبي اللجوء القادمين تجاه أوروبا،
when the vote on leaving had nothing to do with immigration
بينما التصويت لصالح المغادرة يعني قطع العلاقة بموضوع الهجرة
from outside the European Union.
من خارج الإتحاد الأوروبي.
But for a significant majority of the Leave voters
لكن بالنسبة لأغلبية معتبرة لمن صوتوا لخيار المغادرة
the concern was disillusionment with the political establishment.
كان الاهتمام منصباً على خيبة الأمل من المؤسسة السياسية.
This was a protest vote for many,
كان هذا تصويت احتجاجا بالنسبة للكثيرين،
a sense that nobody represented them,
الإحساس بأن لا أحد يمثلهم،
that they couldn't find a political party that spoke for them,
أنهم لم يجدوا حزباً سياسياً يتحدث نيابة عنهم،
and so they rejected that political establishment.
فكانت النتيجة أن رفضوا تلك المؤسسة السياسية.
This replicates around Europe and much of the liberal democratic world.
هذا الأمر يتكرر في أنحاء أوروبا وجزء كبير من العالم الديمقراطي الليبرالي.
We see it with the rise in popularity of Donald Trump in the United States,
نشهد ذلك في الشعبية المتنامية لدونالد ترامب في الولايات المتحدة،
with the growing nationalism of Viktor Orbán in Hungary,
والقومية المتنامية لفيكتور أوربان في هنغاريا،
with the increase in popularity of Marine Le Pen in France.
وأيضاً الشعبية المتزايدة لمارين لو بان في فرنسا.
The specter of Brexit is in all of our societies.
شبح خروج بريطانيا موجود في كل مجتماعتنا.
So the question I think we need to ask is my second question,
لذلك، السؤال الذي أظن أننا بحاجة لطرحه هو سؤالي الثاني،
which is how should we collectively respond?
ألا وهو كيف علينا أن نستجيب بشكل جماعي؟
For all of us who care about creating liberal, open, tolerant societies,
بالنسبة لنا جميعاً من نهتم بخلق مجتمعات ليبرالية ومنفتحة ومتسامحة،
we urgently need a new vision,
بحن بحاجة ماسة إلى رؤية جديدة،
a vision of a more tolerant, inclusive globalization,
رؤية تتسم بعولمة شاملة ومساحة تسامح أكبر،
one that brings people with us rather than leaving them behind.
تصطحب الناس معنا بدلاً من تركهم وراءنا.
That vision of globalization
رؤية العولمة هذه
is one that has to start by a recognition of the positive benefits of globalization.
يجب أن نستهلها بالتعرف على الفوائد الإيجابية للعولمة.
The consensus amongst economists
المتفق عليه بين الإقتصاديين
is that free trade, the movement of capital,
هو أن منطقة تجارة حرة، وحركة رأس المال،
the movement of people across borders
وحركة الناس بحرية عبر الحدود
benefit everyone on aggregate.
تفيد الجميع في المجمل.
The consensus amongst international relations scholars
المتفق عليه بين علماء العلاقات الدولية
is that globalization brings interdependence,
هو أن العولمة تجلب الترابط،
which brings cooperation and peace.
الشيء الذي يجلب بدوره التعاون والسلام.
But globalization also has redistributive effects.
لكن العولمة أيضاً لها آثار إعادة التوزيع.
It creates winners and losers.
فهي تخلق فائزين وخاسرين.
To take the example of migration,
فلو أخذنا الهجرة كمثال،
we know that immigration is a net positive for the economy as a whole
نعلم أن الهجرة هي صافي فائدة للإقتصاد ككل
under almost all circumstances.
تحت كل الظروف تقريباً.
But we also have to be very aware
ولكن يجب علينا أن نكون واعين تماماً
that there are redistributive consequences,
أن هنالك تبعات إعادة توزيع،
that importantly, low-skilled immigration
الشيئ المهم، أن العمالة غير الماهرة
can lead to a reduction in wages for the most impoverished in our societies
قد تقود إلى تقليل الأجور بالنسبة للفئة الأكثر فقراً في مجتمعاتنا
and also put pressure on house prices.
وتشكل ضغطاً كذلك على أسعار المنازل.
That doesn't detract from the fact that it's positive,
ذلك لا ينتقص من حقيقة أنها شيء إيجابي،
but it means more people have to share in those benefits
ولكن ذلك يعني أن عدداً أكبر من الناس لابد أن يشارك في هذه المنافع
and recognize them.
ويتعرف عليها.
In 2002, the former Secretary-General of the United Nations, Kofi Annan,
في العام 2002 ألقى الأمين العام للأمم المتحدة السابق كوفي عنان،
gave a speech at Yale University,
خطاباً في جامعة يال،
and that speech was on the topic of inclusive globalization.
وقد كان ذلك الخطاب يتعلق بموضوع العولمة الشاملة.
That was the speech in which he coined that term.
وقد كان ذلك هو الخطاب الذي صاغ فيه هذا المصطلح.
And he said, and I paraphrase,
وقد قال، مع إعادة صياغتي للنص،
"The glass house of globalization has to be open to all
"بيت العولمة الزجاجي لابد أن يبقى مفتوحاً للجميع
if it is to remain secure.
إذا أريد له أن يظل آمناً.
Bigotry and ignorance
التعصب الأعمى والجهل
are the ugly face of exclusionary and antagonistic globalization."
هما الوجه القبيح للعولمة الإقصائية والعدائية."
That idea of inclusive globalization was briefly revived in 2008
فكرة العولمة الشاملة تلك تم إحياؤها في العام 2008
in a conference on progressive governance
في مؤتمر عن الحكم التقدمي
involving many of the leaders of European countries.
شمل عدداً من قادة الدول الأوروبية.
But amid austerity and the financial crisis of 2008,
ولكن في ظل التقشف والأزمة المالية التي حدثت في العام 2008
the concept disappeared almost without a trace.
اختفى المفهوم تقريباً بلا أثر.
Globalization has been taken to support a neoliberal agenda.
تم توظيف العولمة لخدمة أجندة الليبرالية الجديدة.
It's perceived to be part of an elite agenda
فقد فهمت كجزء من أجندة النخبة
rather than something that benefits all.
بدلاً عن شي يخدم مصلحة الجميع.
And it needs to be reclaimed on a far more inclusive basis
ويجب أن يتم إصلاحها على أساس أكثر شمولاً
than it is today.
مما هي عليه اليوم.
So the question is, how can we achieve that goal?
السؤال الذي يطرح نفسه، كيف لنا أن نحقق ذلك الهدف؟
How can we balance on the one hand addressing fear and alienation
كيف لنا أن نوازن بين معالجة الخوف والعزلة من جهة
while on the other hand refusing vehemently
بينما على الجهة الأخرى الرفض بشدة
to give in to xenophobia and nationalism?
للإذعان لرهاب الأجانب والقومية؟
That is the question for all of us.
ذلك سؤال مطروح علينا جميعاً.
And I think, as a social scientist,
وأعتقد كباحث اجتماعي،
that social science offers some places to start.
أن علم الإجتماع يمدنا ببعض الخيوط للإمساك بها.
Our transformation has to be about both ideas and about material change,
يجب أن يدور التحول حول الأفكار والتغيير الجوهري،
and I want to give you four ideas as a starting point.
وأود إعطاءكم أربعة أفكار كنقطة بداية.
The first relates to the idea of civic education.
الأولى متعلقة بفكرة التعليم المدني.
What stands out from Brexit
ما توضح جلياً من خروج بريطانيا
is the gap between public perception and empirical reality.
هو الفجوة بين التصور العام والواقع التجريبي.
It's been suggested that we've moved to a postfactual society,
فقد اقترح أننا انتقلنا إلى مجتمع واقعي آخر،
where evidence and truth no longer matter,
حيث لم تعد تهم البينة والحقيقة.
and lies have equal status to the clarity of evidence.
وأن الأكاذيب أصبحت في نفس درجة وضوح البينة.
So how can we --
إذاً كيف لنا--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
How can we rebuild respect for truth and evidence into our liberal democracies?
كيف لنا أن نعيد بناء احترام الحقيقة والبينة في الديموقراطيات الليبرالية لدينا؟
It has to begin with education,
يجب أن يبدأ ذلك بالتعليم،
but it has to start with the recognition that there are huge gaps.
ولكن لابد أن يبدأ بالإعتراف أن هناك فجوات كبيرة.
In 2014, the pollster Ipsos MORI
في العام 2014 نشر ايبسوس موري
published a survey on attitudes to immigration,
دراسة تتناول المواقف من الهجرة،
and it showed that as numbers of immigrants increase,
ولقد أوضحت أنه مع ازدياد أرقام المهاجرين،
so public concern with immigration also increases,
فإن القلق العام من الهجرة يزداد أيضاً،
although it obviously didn't unpack causality,
على الرغم من أنه وبشكل واضح لم يفضي إلى السببية،
because this could equally be to do not so much with numbers
بسبب أن هذا وبنفس القدر قد لايغير الكثير مع الأرقام
but the political and media narrative around it.
عكس القصة السياسية والإعلامية حوله.
But the same survey also revealed
ولكن نفس الدراسة كشفت أيضاً
huge public misinformation
تضليلاُ جماهيرياً كبيراً
and misunderstanding about the nature of immigration.
وسوء فهم لطبيعة الهجرة.
For example, in these attitudes in the United Kingdom,
على سبيل المثال، في هذه المواقف في المملكة المتحدة،
the public believed that levels of asylum
اعتقد العامة أن مستويات اللجوء
were a greater proportion of immigration than they were,
مثلت نسبة أكبر من الهجرة مما كانت عليه،
but they also believed the levels of educational migration
ولكنهم أيضاً اعتقدوا أن مستويات الهجرة التعليمية
were far lower as a proportion of overall migration
مثلت نسبة أقل بكثير من مجموع الهجرة
than they actually are.
مقارنة بما كانت عليه في الواقع.
So we have to address this misinformation,
لذا يتوجب علينا معالجة هذا التضليل،
the gap between perception and reality on key aspects of globalization.
المتمثل في الفجوة بين التصور والواقع على الجوانب الرئيسية للعولمة.
And that can't just be something that's left to our schools,
وذلك شيء يجب أن لا يترك لمدارسنا فقط،
although that's important to begin at an early age.
على الرغم من أنه من المهم البدء في عمر مبكر.
It has to be about lifelong civic participation
الأمر يدور حول مشاركة مدنية مدى الحياة
and public engagement that we all encourage as societies.
واشراك الجمهور الشيء الذي يجب أن ندعمه كمجتمعات.
The second thing that I think is an opportunity
الأمر الثاني الذي أراه كفرصة
is the idea to encourage more interaction across diverse communities.
هو فكرة تشجيع مزيد من التفاعل بين المجتمعات المختلفة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
One of the things that stands out for me very strikingly,
واحدة من الأشياء التي تبدت لي بشكل ملفت للنظر،
looking at immigration attitudes in the United Kingdom,
بالنظر في سلوك الهجرة إلى المملكة المتحدةـ
is that ironically, the regions of my country
للمفارقة، أن الأقاليم
that are the most tolerant of immigrants
التي تعتبر الأكثر تسامحاً مع المهاجرين
have the highest numbers of immigrants.
تحتضن أكبر نسبة من المهاجرين.
So for instance, London and the Southeast have the highest numbers of immigrants,
على سبيل المثال، لندن والجنوب الشرقي بها أكبر نسبة من المهاجرين،
and they are also by far the most tolerant areas.
وإلى حد بعيد هي المناطق الأكثر تسامحاً.
It's those areas of the country that have the lowest levels of immigration
أما تلك المناطق من البلاد والتي تضم العدد الأقل من المهاجرين
that actually are the most exclusionary and intolerant towards migrants.
في الواقع تعتبر هي الأكثر إقصائية والأقل تسامحاً تجاه المهاجرين.
So we need to encourage exchange programs.
لذا نحن بحاجة إلى تشجيع برامج تبادل.
We need to ensure that older generations who maybe can't travel
نحن بحاجة أن نضمن أن الأجيال الأكبر سناً الذين قد لا يتاح لهم السفر
get access to the Internet.
أن تتاح لهم إمكانية الوصول للإنترنت.
We need to encourage, even on a local and national level,
نحتاج أن نشجع على المستوى المحلي والقومي،
more movement, more participation,
حركة أكثر ومشاركة أكبر،
more interaction with people who we don't know
وتفاعلا أكثر مع الناس الذين لا نعرفهم
and whose views we might not necessarily agree with.
والذين بالضرورة قد لا نتفق مع وجهات نظرهم.
The third thing that I think is crucial, though,
الشيء الثالث والذي أظن أنه حاسم،
and this is really fundamental,
وهو شيء أساسي للغاية،
is we have to ensure that everybody shares
علينا أن نضمن أن الجميع يشارك
in the benefits of globalization.
في منافع العولمة.
This illustration from the Financial Times post-Brexit is really striking.
هذا الرسم من صحيفة فاينانشال تايمز ما بعد خروج بريطانيا لافت للنظر حقاً.
were those who actually benefited the most materially
كانوا الأكثر انتفاعاً
from trade with the European Union.
من التجارة مع الإتحاد الأوروبي.
But the problem is that those people in those areas
ولكن المشكلة أن أولئك الناس في تلك المناطق
didn't perceive themselves to be beneficiaries.
لا يعتبرون أنفسهم مستفيدين.
They didn't believe that they were actually getting access
لم يصدقوا أنه أمكنهم الوصول
to material benefits of increased trade and increased mobility around the world.
إلى استفادة مادية من ازدياد حركة التجارة والتنقل حول العالم.
I work on questions predominantly to do with refugees,
أعمل على مسائل ذات علاقة وطيدة باللاجئين،
and one of the ideas I spent a lot of my time preaching,
وواحدة من الأفكار التي قضيت الكثير من وقتي أعظ بها،
mainly to developing countries around the world,
وبخاصة للدول النامية حول العالم،
is that in order to encourage the integration of refugees,
أنه من أجل تشجيع إدماج اللاجئين،
we can't just benefit the refugee populations,
لا يمكننا فقط أن ننتفع من تعداد اللاجئين،
we also have to address the concerns of the host communities in local areas.
يجب علينا أيضاً أن نعالج مخاوف المجتمعات المضيفة في المناطق المحلية.
But in looking at that,
وبالنظر إلى ذلك،
one of the policy prescriptions is that we have to provide
واحدة من الوصفات السياسية أنه يجب علينا أن نقدم
disproportionately better education facilities, health facilities,
بشكل غير متناسب مرافق تعليمية ومرافق صحية أفضل،
access to social services
وإمكانية وصول إلى الخدمات الاجتماعية
in those regions of high immigration
في المناطق ذات معدلات الهجرة الأكبر
to address the concerns of those local populations.
لمعالجة مخاوف هؤلاء السكان المحليين.
But while we encourage that around the developing world,
ولكن بينما نشجع ذلك في العالم النامي،
we don't take those lessons home
لا نطبق هذه الدروس في أوطاننا
and incorporate them in our own societies.
وندمجها في مجتمعاتنا.
Furthermore, if we're going to really take seriously
علاوة على ذلك، إذا ما كنا سنأخذ على محمل الجد
the need to ensure people share in the economic benefits,
الحاجة لضمان مشاركة الناس في المنافع الإقتصادية،
our businesses and corporations need a model of globalization
فإن شركاتنا ومؤسساتنا تحتاج إلى نموذج عولمة
that recognizes that they, too, have to take people with them.
يعترف أن عليها،هي أيضا، أن تضم الناس إليها.
The fourth and final idea I want to put forward
الفكرة الرابعة والأخيرة التي أود طرحها
is an idea that we need more responsible politics.
هي أننا بحاجة إلى سياسة أكثر مسؤولية.
There's very little social science evidence
توجد أدلة علوم اجتماعية قليلة جداً
that compares attitudes on globalization.
تقارن السلوكيات في العولمة.
But from the surveys that do exist,
ولكن اعتماداً على الدراسات الموجودة،
what we can see is there's huge variation across different countries
ما نراه هو أن هناك اختلاف كبير في بلدان مختلفة
and time periods in those countries
والفترات الزمنية في تلك البلدان
for attitudes and tolerance
فيما يتعلق بالمواقف والتسامح
of questions like migration and mobility on the one hand
مع مسائل مثل الهجرة والتنقل من جهة
and free trade on the other.
والتجارة الحرة من جهة أخرى.
But one hypothesis that I think emerges from a cursory look at that data
ولكن إحدى الفرضيات التي أظن أنها تبرز من نظرة خاطفة على تلك البيانات
is the idea that polarized societies are far less tolerant of globalization.
هي فكرة أن المجتمعات المستقطبة تعتبر الأقل تسامحاً تجاه العولمة.
It's the societies like Sweden in the past,
مجتمعات مثل السويد في الماضي،
like Canada today,
ومثل كندا اليوم،
where there is a centrist politics,
حيث هناك سياسة وسطية،
where right and left work together,
حيث يعمل اليمين واليسار معاً،
that we encourage supportive attitudes towards globalization.
لذلك فنحن نشجع مواقف داعمة تجاه العولمة.
And what we see around the world today is a tragic polarization,
ما نراه في جميع أنحاء العالم اليوم ما هو إلا استقطاب مأساوي،
a failure to have dialogue between the extremes in politics,
وفشل في خلق حوار بين الفرقاء السياسيين،
and a gap in terms of that liberal center ground
وفجوة من حيث الأرضية الليبرالية المشتركة
that can encourage communication and a shared understanding.
التي يمكن لها أن تشجع التواصل والفهم المشترك.
We might not achieve that today,
قد لا نحقق ذلك اليوم،
but at the very least we have to call upon our politicians and our media
ولكن على الأقل يتوجب علينا دعوة سياسيينا وأجهزة الإعلام لدينا
to drop a language of fear and be far more tolerant of one another.
لإسقاط لغة الخوف وأن نكون أكثر تسامحاً مع بعضنا البعض.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
These ideas are very tentative,
هذه الأفكار مبدئية للغاية،
and that's in part because this needs to be an inclusive and shared project.
وهذا في جزء منه لأنه بحاجة أن يكون مشروعاً شاملاً ومشتركاً.
I am still British.
ما أزال بريطانياً.
I am still European.
ما أزال أوروبياً.
I am still a global citizen.
ما أزال مواطناً عالمياً.
For those of us who believe
بالنسبة للبعض منا الذين يؤمنون
that our identities are not mutually exclusive,
أن هوياتنا لا تستبعد بعضها بعضا،
we have to all work together
يتوجب علينا العمل جنباً إلى جنب،
to ensure that globalization takes everyone with us
لنضمن أن العولمة تصطحبنا جميعاً
and doesn't leave people behind.
ولا تترك الناس خلفنا.
Only then will we truly reconcile democracy and globalization.
حينها فقط سوف نسوي الخلاف بين الديموقراطية والعولمة.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)